A Guide to the Papers of Martin Baskett Shepherd, 1817-1889
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
- Correspondence
  - Letters to John Newton Shepherd 1852-1854 (Box 1)
    - From T[homas] A. Fitzgerald 1852 September 2
    - Oak Hill, from C[harles]; A[gustus] Jones 1854 July 8
    - Oak Hill, Nottoway County, Virginia, from [Charles Agustus Jones] 1854 August 28
  - Mrs. E. O. Mitchell to Mary Kent Shepherd 1852-1855, n.d. (Box 1)
    - 1852 September 4
    - Fairview, Hadensville, Virginia 1853 April 5
    - Fairview, Hadensville, Virginia 1854 May 6
    - 1855 March 16
    - n.y. May 14
    - n.y. May 14
    - n.d.
    - n.d.
  - David Garland Shepherd to Martin Baskett Shepherd 1852-1856 (Box 1)
    - Granville, Jackson County, Tennessee 1852 August 11
    - Granville, Jackson County, Tennessee 1853 January 17
    - Granville, Tennessee 1856 August 18
    - Granville, Tennessee 1856 September 20
    - Granville, Jackson County, Tennessee 1856 September 20
      Relinquish of claims on balance due from Thomas Baker
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence 1852-1876, n.d. (Box 1)
    - Martin Baskett Shepherd, to the voters of Fluvanna County 1852 April 1
      Withdrawing his name as a candidate for the clerkship of the county, and the reasons for the withdrawal
    - Martin Baskett Shepherd, to the voters of Fluvanna County, varied version of above 1852 April
    - R. R. Mason to Mrs. Martin ]Baskett] Shepherd 1858 October 2
      Writing for his wife who is ill, expressing her sorrow that she will not be able to see her, and offering the gift of some fresh meat
    - [ ]amie, [Chal] Grove, to Mrs. Shepherd -- personal, missing acquaintances from Palmyra 1858 November 15
    - Mary [A. Evans], Welton, to Mary Shepherd 1860s
      Yankees being only eleven miles from Richmond, personal and family news
    - Mary A. Evans to "Dear Aunt" [Mary Shepherd] 1860s
      How the families and neighbors sustained visits from the Yankees, personal and family news
    - D. M. Crowell, Rome, New York, to M[artin]; B[askett] Shepherd, Palmyra, Fluvanna County 1874 January
      Feeling "a peculiar sympathy for my friends south," spiritual and religious message, discussion of Joel S. Bacon as a young man
    - Warranty Deed, from the Ohio, Kentucky, and Texas Land Company, State of Ohio, to Martin B. Shepherd, Palmyra, Virginia, for lands in the County of Grayson and State of Texas 1876 December 12
    - Blanche Venable, Cascade, Virginia, to M[artin]; B[askett] Shepherd, Palmyra, Fluvanna County, Virginia 1876 May 8
      Discussion of latest novels read, particularly of Byron, the opening of the Grangers' warehouse in Danville, Virginia
    - [ ] Shepherd to Captain Cleveland n.d.
      Discussing a matter with a man named Albins
    - M. E. C. to "Uncle Martin" [Baskett Shepherd]
      Arranging to have his things moved to the smokehouse for safekeeping
  - Jennie Perkins to Stephen J. Perkins 1853 (Box 1)
    - Valley Union Seminary (Hollins), to Stephen J. Perkins 1883 November 27
      Personal, educational, and religious news and word of persons at the school
  - Benjamin A. Shepherd to Martin Baskett Shepherd 1856 (Box 1)
    - Houston, Texas 1856 February 22
      Inquiring about the progress of his school; concern about the health of "Joe" [Joseph Henry Shepherd] and having an occulist care for him; concern over Mary [Shepherd] and her illness (due to pregnancy); probable plans for a trip to Virginia next summer; personal and family news.
    - Houston, Texas 1856 May 24
      Birth of their baby, Susan Manella "Nelly," on the 5th of March; Mary [Shepherd's] and children's plans to leave New Orleans, Louisiana for travel to Richmond, Virginia and his own visit there and to the northern cities on business
    - Houston, Texas 1856 June 6
      Uncertainty of Mary being able to leave as planned, chiefly due to "Ben's" absence
    - Houston, Texas 1856 June 13
      Mary not having the opportunity to leave, due to Ben's absence; delay in their travel plans
    - Houston, Texas 1856 July 4
      Still contemplating a trip to Virginia but worried about travelling with four babies, especially during the hot weather; discussing possible alternatives; wishing to go to New York and Boston in connection with his business; Ben's illness and poor eyes
    - Montgomery, Alabama 1856 July 23
      Arrived with little Ben and William Perkins and his family by steamboat from Mobile, Alabama; wishing to take Ben to the best occulist in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania
    - Philadelphia, Pennsylvania 1856 August 14
      Dr. Hayes' diagnosis that Ben's eyes would improve not with medical treatment but with overall improved health and vigor and suggestion for a change of climate; death of Shelton [ ] on the 6th; plans for arrival in Virginia and leaving Ben with sister Polly
  - James Meredith Shepherd to Martin Baskett Shepherd 1856
    - Lexington, Tennessee 1856 May 21
      Financial matter between a Mr. Henderson and a Mr. Miles; their father's estate; the current education of his children: John William, twelve, David I., ten; Elizabeth Rebecca, nine; Laura E., seven; and, Helen Mary, four; "our town a great place for drinking and gaming," the legislation repealing the license law for on premises
    - Lexington, Tennessee 1856 September 15
      Note relinquishing all claims due from Thomas Baker and Martin B. Shepherd, administrators of their father's estate
  - Benjamin A. Shepherd (nephew) and Joseph Henry Shepherd to Martin Baskett Shepherd 1856
    - Charleston, South Carolina 1856 March 1
      Introduction from thirteen year old nephew, detailing current education; March 5 --personal and family news from his brother; one of his partner's being in Europe and in St. Croix for the treatment of consumption; being engaged with business, Sunday school, and church matters
  - William M. and Stephen J. Perkins to Col. Joseph Perkins 1857-1858, 1865
  - Farrar Family to their Uncle and Aunt, Martin Baskett and Mary Kent Shepherd 1856-1866
  - Bettie A. and Sallie Leftwich to Mary Kent Shepherd 1858-1860
  - Bettie Mitchell to Mary Kent Shepherd 1858-1860
  - Sallie Leftwich to "Dear Sister," including an inventory of blacks to be divided by the Leftwich family 1860
  - Perrin Farrar to Martin Baskett Shepherd 1860-1871
  - Berta C. Mitchell to Mary Kent Shepherd 1861-1864, n.d.
  - David Garland Shepherd to Martin Baskett Shepherd 1861-1868
  - Benjamin A. Shepherd to Martin Baskett Shepherd 1861-1869
  - O. T. Mitchell to Martin Baskett Shepherd 1862-1867
  - Kate L. Bennett to Martin Baskett Shepherd 1864
  - Ann B. Leftwich to Martin Baskett and Mary Kent Shepherd 1864
  - Letter from J[oseph]; H[enry] Shepherd to Mary Kent Shepherd 1864
  - Martin Baskett Shepherd to William M. Perkins 1866-1867
  - Correspondence of William M. Perkins re Estate of John Newton Shepherd 1867
  - A. L. Shepherd to Martin Baskett Shepherd 1867
  - Bettie A. Leftwich to Martin Baskett Shepherd 1869
  - A. L. Shepherd and Co. to Mrs. Thomas Cleveland 1869 (Box 1)
  - David Garland Shepherd to Martin Baskett Shepherd 1869 (Box 1)
  - William M. Perkins to Thomas Cleveland re Black Laborers 1870 (Box 1)
  - David Garland Shepherd to Martin Baskett Shepherd 1870 (Box 1)
  - Benjamin A. Shepherd to Martin Baskett Shepherd 1871-1872, 1883 (Box 1)
  - William M. Perkins to Thomas Cleveland re Black Laborers brought from Fluvanna County to work in New Orleans 1871 (Box 1)
  - Thomas Shepherd to Martin Baskett Shepherd 1880 (Box 1)
  - D. C. Shepherd to Martin Baskett Shepherd 1883 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence of John Newton Shepherd and his parents, Martin Baskett and Mary Kent Shepherd 1851-1866, n.d., 26 folders (Box 2)
- Personal Papers
  - Martin Baskett Shepherd's trip to New York 1826 (Box 2)
  - Religious Essays written by Martin Baskett Shepherd for the Religious Herald1846-1854, n.d. (Box 2)
  - Obituaries of Family Members 1849-1870 (Box 2)
  - Records of the Fork Baptist Church of Fluvanna County 1849-1865, n.d. (Box 2)
  - Religious Essays written by Martin Baskett Shepherd 1851-1855, n.d. (Box 3)
  - Blacks and the Church 1852-1853, n.d. (Box 3)
  - Educational Essays written by Martin Baskett Shepherd n.d. (Box 3)
  - Lecture Notes taken by John Newton Shepherd at the University of Virginia 1852-1855 (Box 3)
  - Amnesty Oath of Martin Baskett Shepherd 1865 (Box 3)
  - Medical Cures 1871-1879 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous Verse n.d. (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous Food and Household Recipes n.d. (Box 3)
  - Material copied from the Autobiography of Martin Baskett Shepherdn.d. (Box 3)
- Financial and Legal Papers
  - Estate of David Shepherd 1823-1850 (Box 3)
  - Business Papers of Martin Baskett Shepherd 1828-1849 (Box 3)
  - Estate of Dabney Minor 1834-1835 (Box 3)
  - Newspaper Receipts 1838-1860 (Box 3)
  - Deeds and Surveys pertaining to Martin Baskett Shepherd's Land in Fluvanna County 1834-1857 (Box 3)
  - Estate of Stephen Farrar 1838-1870 (Box 3)
  - Account Books and Record of Crop Yields 1847-1867 (Box 3)
  - Business Papers of Martin Baskett Shepherd 1850-1889, n.d., 4 folders (Box 3)